<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Astrologia accusata pariter &amp; condemnata. Or The diabolical art of judicial astrologie, receiving the definitive sentence of final condemnation: being delivered in this following discourse, where the said art is briefly and manifestly opened, justly arraigned, diligently examined, and experimentally condemned by him, who was a student in the same. / By John Raunce, sometime a practitioner of astrologie, and student in the magick art.</title>
            <author>Raunce, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E618_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206349</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865515</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 95:E618[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Astrologia accusata pariter &amp; condemnata. Or The diabolical art of judicial astrologie, receiving the definitive sentence of final condemnation: being delivered in this following discourse, where the said art is briefly and manifestly opened, justly arraigned, diligently examined, and experimentally condemned by him, who was a student in the same. / By John Raunce, sometime a practitioner of astrologie, and student in the magick art.</title>
                  <author>Raunce, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Clowes, for W. Learner, at the Blackmore in Bishopsgate-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 2d.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117760:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſtrologia accuſata pariter &amp; Condemnata.</hi> OR THE DIABOLICAL ART OF Judicial Aſtrologie, RECEIVING THE DEFINITIVE SENTENCE OF FINAL CONDEMNATION: BEING Delivered in this following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, where the ſaid Art is briefly and manifeſtly opened, juſtly arraigned, diligently examined, and experimentally condemned by him, who was a <hi>Student</hi> in the ſame.</p>
            <q>Omnis planta quam non plantavit Pater ille meus coeleſtis, eradicabitur. <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 15.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOHN RAUNCE, <hi>Sometime a practitioner of</hi> Aſtrologie, <hi>and</hi> Student <hi>in the Magick Art.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> J. Clowes, <hi>for</hi> W. Learner, <hi>at the</hi> Blackmore <hi>in</hi> Biſhopſgate-ſtreete, 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117760:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117760:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY deſire is in this ſhort <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> to diſcloſe a part of my mind unto thee, concerning <hi>Judicial Aſtrology,</hi> and if it might be, to perſwade thee, not to ſpend thy ſhort and precious time, in the ſtudy and practice of this abominable <hi>Art;</hi> for I have been a <hi>Student</hi> in this very <hi>Art,</hi> againſt which I now write: alſo I was not quiet, nor at peace in my mind, until ſuch time as I had ſeen all the ſecrets of the ſame. Now the time being come, in which I had attained unto my hearts deſire, then did I blindly rejoyce in my condition, and thought with my ſelf, that I had now gotten the knowledge of that, which would for ever make me wiſe: thus having attained unto my Hearts deſire, and being in my youthful Age, I here with-held no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from my ſelf, which might ſeem to give my mind content: So I mounting from degree to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, upon the ſlippery ſcale of curioſity, at length I came to the height of uncertain principles; which when I was thus high gone, yet here found no reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place, wherefore I beholding that there was more then I yet underſtood, then did I here ſeek for the knowledge of thoſe things alſo, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of which things was not from me with-held. Now I having gone to the ground of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> I could then diſpute of the events of things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Loe
<pb facs="tcp:117760:3"/>
here I did vainly glory in my ſelf, as if that by the greatneſs of my Art, and the quickneſs of my inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, made a Conqueſt of <hi>Plutoes</hi> Dominion. But this vain conceit of mine, did not continue long; for when I was in the prime of my practice, the <hi>Lord God</hi> from Heaven confounded my wiſdom, and deſtroyed all my <hi>Babylonian</hi> skill. Now my <hi>Reader,</hi> it may be here thou doſt expect the ſtory of my converſion from my diabolical practiſes, but I ſhall ſay very little of that at this time; for all that I ſhall declare of it at preſent, is only thus, <hi>viz.</hi> when I was in rhe prime of my diabolical ways, one day I being in my ſtudy, very earneſt in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the cauſe of future events: at this very time, when I thought my ſelf to be at peace, and in a happy condition, then came the <hi>Lord God</hi> in a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible voice into my heart, and whereſoever I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came for many days after, I continually <hi>heard this moſt doleful ſound in my mind, viz.</hi> After all ſuch things only wicked men ſeek. And as I heard this voice ſounding in my heart, ſo alſo I had my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience accuſing me, that I was one of thoſe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, becauſe I did ſpend my precious time in ſearching out the cauſe of thoſe things which no man can attain unto, but by diabolical Learning. Wherefore my <hi>Reader,</hi> it is not without cauſe, that I have taken upon me to declare the vileneſs of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrological Predictions.</hi> For if I am raiſed up by the <hi>Lord God,</hi> to be an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> to gain-ſay and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Art of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> then aſſuredly I ſhall be able, to ſtand before the faces of the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> to witneſs that which here I have delivered. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, I ſay unto all perſons whatſoever, before
<pb facs="tcp:117760:3"/>
whom this Book of mine ſhall come, how that I have not gone raſhly nor inconſiderately to work, in that I have taken in hand to declare againſt that wicked <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Judicial Aſtrology:</hi> Alſo I ſay I would them to know, that I have ſet my ſelf down ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to conſider, what it would coſt me at the higheſt price, which if the worſt come, I know what I have to do. And as for the ſcoffs and jeeres of all my <hi>Antagoniſts,</hi> or any other whatſoever, <hi>I</hi> ſay their ſcoffing and jeering is no more to me, then the dirt that doth hang on my ſhoes; which dirt at my pleaſure, I can ſhake off, when and where I pleaſe. Now if any man be unſatisfied in what I have here written, againſt the ſaid <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Judicial Aſtrology,</hi> becauſe I do deny the ſaid <hi>Art</hi> to be lawful. Therefore I ſay unto all ſuch men, that if they can prove <hi>Astrology</hi> a lawful <hi>Art</hi> by ſounder and better <hi>Arguments</hi> grounded upon the <hi>Scripture</hi> and reaſon, then it is here, or can elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where by me be denyed, then am I willing to ſubmit, and ſo for the preſent farewell,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN RAUNCE, <hi>Of the Burrough of Chip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Wickham, in the County of Buckingham.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>November</hi> 8. 1650,</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:117760:4"/>
            <head>The Prological Oration of the <hi>Authour,</hi> to all <hi>Practitioners</hi> of <hi>Astrology,</hi> and unto all other Perſons whatſoever, that are lovers of the ſame.</head>
            <l>BEhold you vain <hi>Aſtrologers</hi>
            </l>
            <l>who gazing on the Sky,</l>
            <l>Search out the motions of the Stars</l>
            <l>for to Divine thereby;</l>
            <l>Of the particular events</l>
            <l>and ends of things which are,</l>
            <l>Known by the name of contingents</l>
            <l>which no Art can declare;</l>
            <l>Whoſe Rules are only natural</l>
            <l>and are contain'd within</l>
            <l>The bounds of learning liberal,</l>
            <l>which is without all ſin.</l>
            <l>Where will you then a reſting place</l>
            <l>for this vain Art out find,</l>
            <l>That ſo it may not have diſgrace</l>
            <l>being numbred with the kind</l>
            <l>Of wicked and ungodly Arts,</l>
            <l>which are both vain and ill,</l>
            <l>And doth reſide in rotten hearts</l>
            <l>for to fulfill their will.</l>
            <l>For all ſuch men as do profeſs</l>
            <l>and folkes which ſeek this skill,</l>
            <l>All ſuch the Devil doth poſſeſs</l>
            <l>made Captives at his will?</l>
            <l>When born their Child, then ſuddenly</l>
            <l>the hour muſt be ſought;</l>
            <l>And ſo they think to know thereby</l>
            <l>It's fortune good or naught.</l>
            <l>Or if on them doth fall ſome loſſe,</l>
            <l>contrary to their will,</l>
            <l>Then from ſome Planet came that croſſe</l>
            <l>who was not good but ill.</l>
            <l>Alſo if God on them doth lay</l>
            <l>for ſin ſome ſore Diſeaſe,</l>
            <l>Then preſently they ſend away</l>
            <l>to <hi>Ekrons</hi> God for eaſe.</l>
            <l>Or if they fear their time is nigh,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> they ſend,</l>
            <l>To know if then they needs muſt dye</l>
            <l>and may not more amend.</l>
            <l>Even as King <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> who</l>
            <l>when on his bed did lie,</l>
            <l>To <hi>Baal-zebub</hi> (ſaid he) now go,</l>
            <l>and ask when I ſhall dye.</l>
            <l>And now then my own Countrymen,</l>
            <l>my councel ſee you take,</l>
            <l>Conſider what your Art is then,</l>
            <l>and from your ſin awake.</l>
            <l>Let no man ſay I here diſpute</l>
            <l>contrary to my mind</l>
            <l>As if I here were deſtitute,</l>
            <l>and this way would it find.</l>
            <l>For I my ſelf have ſometime been</l>
            <l>a <hi>Student</hi> in this skill,</l>
            <l>All ſecrets in it I have ſeen</l>
            <l>to ſatisfie my will.</l>
            <l>Now to the Lord be all the praiſe</l>
            <l>who of his own free grace,</l>
            <l>Hath brought me from my wicked ways</l>
            <l>and ſet me in this place;</l>
            <l>That ſo I ſhould a witneſs be</l>
            <l>againſt theſe wicked Arts,</l>
            <l>As here it is ſet forth by me</l>
            <l>to the grief of your hearts.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN RAUNCE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117760:4"/>
            <head>A <hi>DISCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RSE</hi> AGAINST Judicial Aſtrology.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER I.</hi> Of Iudicial Aſtrology, what it is, the original of it, who was the Authour thereof, by what Names or Titles the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of it are called, and their Profeſſion what it promiſeth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as I have taken in hand, to ſet forth to the view of my <hi>Countreymen,</hi> the nature of that <hi>Art</hi> which is known by the name of <hi>Iudicial Aſtrology,</hi> that now my <hi>Doctrine</hi> may be underſtood of all men;<note place="margin">What Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie that is, which is by the Authour called Iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</note> I think it convenient here to ſet forth in few words, what I mean by <hi>Iudicial Aſtrology,</hi> which is briefly thus defined, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>Iudicial Aſtrologie</hi> I underſtand <hi>Aſtrological Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> in which the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> doth foretel the particular events of things belonging to man. For as much as it is my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117760:5"/>
deſire, that my <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> may know and underſtand my mind plainly:<note place="margin">See my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaiſt Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, Page <hi>2.</hi> line <hi>2. 3. 4.</hi>
                  </note> therefore I declare that this aforeſaid <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Iudicial Aſtrologie,</hi> is a ſecret diabolical <hi>Divination,</hi> as it is elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where by me divulged. Moreover, I do affirm the ſaid <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> to be full of Idolatry and ſuperſtition, and is contrary unto the <hi>Scripture,</hi> as I ſhall here manifeſt and prove to all rational men, whom I deſire wel to conſider this firſt,<note place="margin">Note here</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> That no <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> can or is able (according to the <hi>Rules</hi> of their ſaid <hi>Art</hi>) to predict or foretell the event or end of any particular thing belonging unto man, but by their ſuperſtitious and Idolatrous obſerving and regarding of time, that this regarding of time is (as I have ſaid) ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and Idolatry, is evident from the words of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to be ſeen,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10.11.</note> in <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10.11. verſes. You may there find many unlawful things rehearſed and condemned for abominable and wicked practiſes; amongſt which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful obſervations, there is alſo named this wicked Art of obſerving of time, in theſe words; <hi>Let none be found among you that is a regarder of times:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> here is to be noted, how that all obſerving and regarding of time is here forbidden and condemned,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>3.</hi> chap. from the <hi>1.</hi> verſe to the <hi>8.</hi> verſ.</note> which is not agreeable to the <hi>Scripture:</hi> now whereas <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>there is an appointed time, and a time to every purpoſe under Heaven. A time to be born, and a time to die,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Solomon</hi> doth not here ſay, that one time is better then another to be born in; nor that one time is worſe then another to die in; again he ſaith, <hi>there is a time to love, and a time to hate, a time of Warre, and a time of peace.</hi> Yet he doth not ſay, that Men and Women do either love or hate each other, according to the ſeveral diſpoſitions of the ſignificators of their <hi>Nativities.</hi> Neither doth <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay that <hi>Warres</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> proceed of, or from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the <hi>Planets:</hi> nor yet that one time is better to go to warre in then another, becauſe of the poſitious of the <hi>Starres.</hi> Now we may ſee how that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, and ſo with him all other wiſe men, that there is an appointed time for every thing under the whole Heaven. The ſayings of this wiſe man <hi>Solomon,</hi> are agreeable to the mind and will
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117760:5"/>
of <hi>God</hi> revealed in the <hi>Scripture;</hi> for the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently hold forth unto us, that there is a time for all things to be accompliſhed and finiſhed in; but in no one place of the <hi>Scripture</hi> is it ſaid, that one time is better then another, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Starres,</hi> or the poſitions of the <hi>Heavens,</hi> for to do the aforeſaid things: wherefore we may clearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold our <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> what it is; for take from it that which the word of <hi>God</hi> doth forbid and condemn, and then it will be of no worth to the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> becauſe it will then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be a beggerly <hi>Art,</hi> that hath no reſting or abiding place, in any part of good learning. But to return to our matter again, I ſay, that <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is an unlawful <hi>Art,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of time, the firſt thing why A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie is unlawful. Deut. <hi>18.</hi> v. <hi>10. 11. 14.</hi>
                  </note> and ought not to be practiſed in a <hi>Chriſtian Commonwealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the thing without which <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> cannot be practiſed, is by, and in the <hi>Scripture</hi> plainly forbidden and condemned: now this thing is the regarding of times, which you may ſee, is poſitively condemned in the 18. Chapter of <hi>Deut.</hi> v. 10. <hi>Let none be found among you that is a regarder of times.</hi> Now that the name <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is not here named I confeſs; but that the practiſe of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, is evident from what I have, and ſhall ſet forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid <hi>Art.</hi> In the next place I will declare to the World (ſo far as I know) who was the firſt inventer of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie,</hi> that ſo they, who are ignorant of this ſecret <hi>Art,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The original of Aſtrologie, who was the Inventor of it.</note> may underſtand from whence it came, and who was the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> of it, and thereby they may the better judge of its il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legality, according to the judgments of many very learned men: the invention of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is attributed to the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills;</hi> wherefore I have for the witneſſing of the ſaid poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Authority of that learned man, <hi>G. Carleton, Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> whoſe words are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">vide. Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logomania, fol. <hi>57.</hi> Tertul. Lib. de Idololatria. Origen. Hom. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Aſtrologie, is by many learntd men attributed to the Devills.</hi> With whom agree the ſayings of many ancient Writers, as <hi>Tertullian, Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> and <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> with others who ſhall be mentioned in their proper places: hereupon it is apparent from what theſe <hi>Authours</hi> have written in their own works, that <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is by them
<pb facs="tcp:117760:6"/>
condemned for a wicked <hi>Art,</hi> whoſe original is from the <hi>Devils,</hi> and therefore is not fit to be ſuffered in a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> much leſs in and amongſt thoſe, who are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and Profeſſors of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">St. Auguſt. Lib. de Doc. Chr. Aug. Lib. de nat. Daemon.</note> for as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>it is a great madneſs and folly to go about to tell by the Starrs, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, actions, and events of men;</hi> which ſaith he, true <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> piety expelleth and condemneth. Alſo the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour affirmeth, that <hi>it is not lawful for any Chriſtian to caſt Nativities.</hi> Theſe things which are here alledged out of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,</hi> (I think) are able to ſatisfie any rational man, that <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is a wicked <hi>Art,</hi> becauſe as he himſelf confeſſeth in his book of Confeſſions,<note place="margin">Chamber. ex Auguſt.</note> that he was of that ungodly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> for his words are theſe, <hi>viz. Now alſo I had renounced the falſe Predictions of Aſtrologers, whom Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and true piety expelleth and condemneth:</hi> the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> cannot ſay (except they will lie) that this great <hi>Doctor,</hi> and ancient <hi>Father</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writ againſt <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> through the weakneſs of his learning; nor can they ſay that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned their <hi>Art,</hi> becauſe he did not know it; but we find that he ſpeaketh againſt the ſaid <hi>Art,</hi> becauſe he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of its unſoundneſs. In the nexr place, I ſuppoſe it is convenient to ſay a little of the Names and Titles of the profeſſors of this ſaid <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Judicial Aſtrologie,</hi> they are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or known by there names,<note place="margin">Names be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing unto the Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, both in Engliſh and Latine.</note> 
                  <hi>viz. Aſtrologers, Prognoſticators, Almanack-makers, Figure-flingers, Wiſe-men, Cunning-men, Wizards, Magicians, Starre-gazers;</hi> with many ſuch ſtrange names they are called, and in latine, <hi>Chaldae, Aſtrologi, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematici, Planetarij, Magi, Genethliaci, Babylonij, Divini, Fatidici, &amp;c.</hi> this which is ſaid already of the Names of theſe Profeſſors of the aforeſaid <hi>Art,</hi> ſhall ſuffice for the preſent; but to proceed, now I am to ſhew what this abominable Profeſſion promiſeth to perform:<note place="margin">What the Art of Aſtrologie, promiſeth to perform.</note> wherefore you are to underſtand, that <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> promiſeth to foretel what ſhall be the iſſue, event or end, of any thing belonging to man, which things the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do ſay, are ſignified by the 12. houſes of Heaven: theſe are ſome of thoſe things which the 12. houſes are ſaid (by the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi>) to ſignifie, <hi>viz.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117760:6"/>
That the firſt houſe ſignifieth the Life and Body of him that is born, or doth aske a queſtion: the ſecond his Riches, the third,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the twelve Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note>
                  <hi>Brethren and Siſters; the fourth, his Parents; the fifth, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; the ſixth, ſickneſs, the ſeaventh, Marriage; the eighth, Death; the ninth, Religion and God; the tenth, Rule and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; the eleventh, Hope and truſt; the twelfth, private e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies:</hi> theſe, and ſuch like things as theſe are, the <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> do buſie themſelves about, to ſearch out their Events; for ſo much as theſe things aforeſaid, are by the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> feigned to belong to the 12, houſes of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and that they can by the motions and influences of the <hi>Starres,</hi> know what ſhall be the event and end of theſe, or any ſuch things: therefore I ſay and affirm, that no man can by the <hi>Starres,</hi> know what ſhall be the iſſue or event of theſe, or any ſuch things: Alſo, that the <hi>Stars</hi> do not ſignifie any ſuch things as theſe are: Likewiſe I deny, that your twelve houſes can ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie any of theſe things, or any ſuch as theſe are. Moreover I denie, that any man is able by any lawful Learning, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to ſo much knowledge as to know thereby, what ſhall be the iſſue, event; or end of theſe aforeſaid things, or of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other belonging to Man. Yet notwithſtanding, what is here delivered, <hi>viz.</hi> (that no man is able by any lawful <hi>Art,</hi> to attain to ſo much knowledge therein, by good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful learning, as to know thereby what ſhall be the particular events of things belonging to Man:) yet I ſay, I would not have any man think, that it is my judgement, that the <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger</hi> doth not ſometimes by his Art, predict or foretel the events of ſome things belonging to man. But this is that which I ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> That no man can by any lawful Art, come to any ſuch knowledg of future events; but as for <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> and ſuch vain men as they are; I confeſs, that they may by their knowledge and skill in filthy and unclean Arts, (ſuch as is <hi>Judicial Aſtrologie,</hi> with <hi>Magick,</hi> and the like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Arts) come to knowe ſomewhat of future events,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. <hi>chap. v.</hi> 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19.</note> through the inſtigation of the <hi>Devil,</hi> by the permiſſion of <hi>God;</hi> for did not the <hi>Witch</hi> at <hi>Endor,</hi> with the help of the <hi>Devil,</hi> predict or foretel to <hi>King Saul,</hi> what ſhould be his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117760:7"/>
end? which prediction proved true. Now who can prove the going of <hi>Saul</hi> to aske Councel of the <hi>Witch,</hi> or the practice of the <hi>Witch,</hi> in foretelling by the <hi>Devil</hi> the ruine of <hi>Saul;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.6.</note> I ſay where is he that can prove it lawful, becauſe the event anſwered to the Prediction? And yet our <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> have no better Arguments to prove the legality of their Art, of <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> but only becauſe the event falleth out, to be according to the <hi>Prediction;</hi> for when any one queſtioneth with them about the legality of their Art of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi>) then ſhall you have them, to prove the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of their Art. Rehearſe certain <hi>Hiſtorical Predictions</hi> which proved true by the events of the things foretold, and ſo to ſay with Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sir Chriſt: Heydon in his Defence, page <hi>195.</hi>
                  </note> who ſaith, <hi>that he for his own part doth freely confeſs, that there is no one thing that hath made him ſo confident in the validity of this art, as that which he hath ſeen to fall out true.</hi> Now here you may behold that this great <hi>Champion</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh Aſtrologers</hi> after that he had made a long and tedious diſcourſe for the defence of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> at length thinking with himſelf that all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Arguments</hi> were too feeble to prove what he had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, doth here in this place, lay down as his ſtrongeſt <hi>Argument,</hi> (which as himſelf ſaith) made him ſo confident of the validity of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. Lilly in his Introduct. page <hi>148.</hi>
                  </note> and it is this, <hi>viz. The event falling out, according to the Prediction.</hi> Now where is he, that by this <hi>Argument,</hi> is able to prove <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> a lawful <hi>Art?</hi> Almoſt ſuch another Argument, but to the very ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is to be ſeen in the works of Mr. <hi>Wil: Lilly,</hi> who wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the markes, moles or ſcarres, that the Querent hath, ſaith that the verity thereof, hath been one main argument of his engaging in all the parts of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> ſo far. But if Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> hath no better Arguments to prove the verity of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> by, aſſuredly he will not be able to prove the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality of the <hi>Art,</hi> which he as yet profeſſeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:117760:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That <hi>Judicial Aſtrologie</hi> is a vain and fooliſh <hi>Art,</hi> being full of Idolatrous and ſuperſtitious Fables contrary to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and the practice thereof is a Diabolical Divination.</head>
               <p>THe vanity and fooliſhneſs of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aſtrologie is a vain and fooliſh art. Eccleſ. <hi>8.</hi> Chap. <hi>6. 7.</hi> verſes.</note> may many wayes be proved. But to begin, I will bring the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of that wiſe man <hi>King Solomon,</hi> who ſaith, that <hi>for to every purpoſe there is a time and judgement, becauſe the miſery of man is great upon him; for he knoweth not that which ſhall be: for who can tell him when it ſhall be?</hi> Now from this ſaying of <hi>Solomon,</hi> it is very apparent, that none can know the future events of things belonging to man; for he po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively affirmeth, <hi>that no man knoweth that which ſhall be, or who can tell when it ſhall be?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers,</hi> and the vanity of <hi>Aſtrologie.</hi>
                  </note> here you may ſee <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> to be unwiſe, and their Art of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> to be a vain and fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Art; for that which the wiſeſt of men ſaith cannot be known, that do they take upon them for to foretel: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the vanity and fooliſhneſs of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> doth herein appear.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe it hath no one place of the word of <hi>God</hi> to warrant its legality.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe the <hi>Scripture</hi> is not only ſilent in the Commendations thereof; but becauſe it is full of plain ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences which declare openly the fooliſhneſs and vanity of the ſaid Art, in that the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth deride at the <hi>Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners</hi> thereof, and condemneth the practice of it as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, as it is to be ſeen in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 47. ch. &amp; the 13. &amp; 14 verſes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 47. <hi>c. v.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. <hi>c. v.</hi> 2.</note>
                  <hi>Let now the</hi> Aſtrologers, <hi>the</hi> Star-gazers, <hi>the monethly</hi> Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticators <hi>ſtand up, and ſave thee from theſe things which ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117760:8"/>
come upon thee. Behold, they ſhall be as ſtubble, the fire ſhall burn them, they ſhall not deliver themſelves from the power of the flame, &amp;c.</hi> Again, the practice, and the Practitioners thereof are condemned, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. chap. 2. verſe. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, learn not the way of the Heathen, and be not diſmayed at the ſignes of Heaven, for the Heathen are diſmayed at them, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aſtrologers do ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly regard times, as by imagining one time to be better then another, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Planet that is, Lord of the hour, as is ſet forth hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and this is condemned Deut. <hi>18.10.</hi>
                  </note>Thirdly, <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is a vain and fooliſh Art, becauſe that the regarding of time, without which, <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be practiſed, is by and in the <hi>Scripture</hi> condemned for an abomination, as it doth appear in the 18. of <hi>Deut.</hi> and the 14. verſe, which ſaith thus. <hi>For theſe Nations which thou ſhalt poſſeſs, hearkened unto obſervers of times, and unto Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; but as for thee, the Lord thy God hath not ſuffered thee ſo to do.</hi> And as you may ſee in the 12. verſe, aforegoing in the ſame Chap. theſe words, <hi>viz. For all that do theſe things are an abomination unto the Lord: and becauſe of theſe abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Lord thy God doth drive them out from before thee.</hi> Wherefore my beloved <hi>Countreymen,</hi> abandon theſe your <hi>Aſtrological</hi> follies, which if you do not do, I proclaim from the <hi>Lord God,</hi> that deſtruction ſhall come upon you, which you ſhall not foreſee by all your art of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> and when it is upon you, then ſhall you behold your ſelves in miſery, but you ſhall not be able to help your ſelves by all your <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> skill; conſider what I ſay. But from this I haſten to the next thing, which is this, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is full of Idolatrous and ſuperſtitious fables, contrary to the <hi>Scripture:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aſtrologie is full of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Fables.</note> now to the end that this poſition may be made manifeſt: therefore in the firſt place I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with your Houſes of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and I ſay that thoſe ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, which you give of them, are ſuperſtitious Fables; but to the end my <hi>Reader</hi> may underſtand what thoſe ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications are: therefore I do inſert them into this figure following, according as they are appropriated to the twelve Houſes by the <hi>Aſtrologians.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <p n="1">1 Life and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of him that is born, or doth ask the Queſtion; this is the Horoſcope angle.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Goods, Traffick, Subſtance, Riches, Gain, Damage, Loſs, Wealth or Povertie.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Kindred, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, Siſters, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins, ſmall Journeys, Faith and Religion, Changes.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Fathers, Houſes, Heritages, Lands, Tenements, hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Treaſures, end of any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Man.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 Children, Gifts, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, Pleaſures, Plays, Voluptuouſneſs, Banqueting, Bravery, Dancing.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Grief, Sickneſs, Infirmities, the Qualitie &amp; Cauſe of it, Curable or not Curable.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Wives, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, Suits, Quarrels, Strife, known Enmitie, Debate, Love queſtions.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Death, Sadneſs, long Torments, envie the Qualitie of Death, Inherit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 God, Religion, Wiſdom, Faith, Science, Voyage, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, Sects, Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes, Sacrifices, Dreams.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 Honour, Dignities, Offices, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Governers, Rulers, Eſtimation, Profeſſion, Action.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 Friends, Companions, Hope, Confidence, Favour, Help, Succour, Praiſe, Eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
                  <p n="12">12 Private Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Witches, Captivitie, Priſons, Torment, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, Sadneſs, Hate.</p>
               </figure>
               <p>There are many other ſignifications belonging to theſe 12. Houſes, which are ſo many in number, that it would be over tedious for me to name them every one; for they are ſo manifold, according to the judgement of Mr. <hi>Lilley</hi> in his introduction page 50. where he ſaith, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing appertaining to the life of man in this World, which in one way or other hath not relation to one of the twelve Houſes of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and as the 12. ſignes are appropriate to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117760:9"/>
particular Members of Mans Body;<note place="margin">Mr. Lilly his Intred. page <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note> ſo alſo do the 12. Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes repreſent not only the ſeveral parts of man, but his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, quality of life and living, and the curioſity and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our fore-fathers in <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> was ſuch, as they have alotted to every houſe a particular ſignification, and ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed humane accidents throughout the whole 12. Houſes, as he that underſtands the queſtions appertaining to each Houſe, ſhall not want ſufficient grounds whereon to judge or give a rational anſwer upon any contingent acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,<note place="margin">That the ſignes cannot ſignifie the particular Members of Mans Body, neither can the Houſes ſignifie his actions, life, or living.</note> and ſucceſs thereof, thus far Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> with his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers the <hi>Aſtrologers:</hi> And now here again I ſay, that whatſoever Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> hath ſaid, or any of his Fore-fathers affirmed of the aforeſaid poſitions, is by me denied from theſe conſiderations.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I ſay, for as much as there is not a corporal <hi>Heaven,</hi> repreſenting the form and nature of a humane body; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do denie, that the ſeveral parts, life and actions of a humane body, can be appropiated thereunto; for becauſe that thing which doth repreſent another thing in body, muſt have the very ſelf-ſame form of the thing repreſented. So that if the ſeveral parts of Mans Body be appropriated to the 12. houſes and ſignes then muſt the houſes and ſignes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the body of Man in form and ſhape; but how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly erroneous this aſſertion is to all reaſon, is proved thus.</p>
               <p>Firſt I ſay, that the houſes cannot repreſent the body of Man, becauſe that they are only imaginary circumſtances in the circumference of the 9. <hi>Heaven.</hi> Wherefore or as much as that the houſes and ſignes have but onely an imaginary being in form and ſhape: therefore they cannot be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to the particular Members of Mans Body, becauſe the Body of Man hath a viſible and real Being in form and ſhape. which the 12. houſes and ſignes have not, becauſe they are only imaginary things as I ſaid before. Now ſeeing I have from ſufficient grounds, denied that the 12. houſes and ſignes can be appropriated unto the particular parts of Mans Body: In the next place I am to write of the life and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117760:9"/>
of man, for this is the poſition of the <hi>Aſtrologers, viz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The quality of the life &amp; actions of Man, cannot be known by the Houſes, nor from the ſignes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> The 12. Houſes repreſent not only the ſeveral parts of Mans Body; but his actions, quality of his life and living: this Poſition is already afore by me denied, and I have given reaſons for my ſo doing. But to the end, my Reader may be the better able to judge between me and my <hi>Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſts:</hi> Therefore I ſay, that the quality of the life and actions of Man, cannot be known by the Houſes, nor from the Stars or ſignes of Heaven: which thing although I have ſpread abroad ſufficient Arguments for the proof of what I have delivered, yet nevertheleſs, this I ſay again, that for as much as the 12. Signes, as alſo the 12. Houſes of the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> are only imaginary things, ſeigned by the <hi>Aſtrologians:</hi> therefore I deny, that the quality of the life and actions of Man, can be known by the Houſes, or from the 12. Signes of Heaven; becauſe that no conceived <hi>Idaea,</hi> which is as it were a ſubſtance, but is not a real ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in being, can repreſent the humane nature of Man, which is a rea ſubſtance, and hath a viſible being: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing, the Houſes and Signes cannot truly and really repreſent the Body of Man, in ſubſtance, form, and being: Therefore I ſay, that the quality of the life and actions of man cannot be known by the Houſes, nor yet from the Signes of Heaven; for that thing, which doth not truly and really in nature, repreſent the very ſubſtance, form, and natural Being of the thing repreſented, cannot in any wiſe ſignifie the quality of the being; nor yet the nature of the actings of the thing repreſented: from which Argument I infer this concluſion following which is this: That for as much as the 12. Houſes and Signes do not truly and really repreſent the very ſubſtance, form, and natural being of Man: therefore I ſay, that the quality of the life and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Man, cannot be known by,<note place="margin">Mr. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins againſt Witch-craft. page <hi>620.</hi>
                  </note> nor from the Houſes and Signes of Heaven aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Now then in this place, to inſert ſomething out of the works of that godly Man, Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> I judge it very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for theſe two Reaſons.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117760:10"/>
Firſt, becauſe he was a very godly man, and therefore all men ought the more readily to believe that which he wrote to be truth. Secondly, becauſe he was a <hi>Student</hi> in the ſaid Art of <hi>Judicial Aſtrologie;</hi> and therefore he was the better able to judge of the legality or illegality of the Art of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</hi> Now what he faith of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> you may ſee in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of <hi>Witch-craft,</hi> page 620. where his words are to this purpoſe, <hi>viz. That divination by the Starres, is commonly called Judicial Aſtrologie, of which we may read, Deut.</hi> 18.10.11. where the Holy Ghoſt doth of purpoſe reckon up all thoſe kind of develiſh Arts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10.11.</note> whereby men have dealings and ſociety with <hi>Satan,</hi> either in divining or practiſing: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which this is the ſecond.</p>
               <p>The word there uſed may carry a double ſence, for it ſignifieth either him that obſerveth times: under which acception <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is comprehended, or him that obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the Cloudes;<note place="margin">Megnonen.</note> and howſoever, the beſt learned Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters do diſſent about the Notation of it, yet all agree in this, that the profeſſion of divining by the Starres, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: and that it is to be numbred among the reſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the prohibition, may further appear by other places of <hi>Scripture,</hi> as in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 47.13.14. where the <hi>Lord</hi> threatneth the ſame judgements againſt the <hi>Diviners</hi> by the <hi>Starres,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 47.13.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.2.</note> that he doth againſt <hi>Sooth-ſayers,</hi> and <hi>Magicians.</hi> Again in <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Inchanters, Aſtrologers,</hi> and <hi>Sorcerers,</hi> are joyned together, as being all ſent for about the ſame buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>viz. To expound the Kings Dream.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelf have alotted the ſame puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> which he hath to the <hi>Sooth-ſayer</hi> and <hi>Magician,</hi> and account them all one; it is manifeſt, that divining by the <hi>Starrs,</hi> ought to be held as a ſuperſtitious kind of <hi>Divination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> hath declared againſt the Art of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> whereby it doth appear from that which hath been delivered, that <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is contrary unto the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and is alſo full of idolatrous and ſuperſtitious Fables; for it doth manifeſtly appear to be fabulous, and to abound with ſuperſtition and Idolatry, in your Planetary days and hours;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117760:10"/>
for thus ſay you <hi>Aſtrologers, viz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bacon. Ganivetus.</note> That <hi>Saturday</hi> is not a good day for work, becauſe of the <hi>Planet Saturn;</hi> for ſaith <hi>Gani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetus,</hi> if any one cometh to aske councel in the hour of an evil <hi>Planet, viz. Saturn</hi> or <hi>Mars,</hi> it is a ſuſpition rather to evil then to good.</p>
               <p>Again ſaith another,<note place="margin">Haly. Abenragel.</note> the hours of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> ought to be abhorr'd in all things; for ſaith he, you were beſt to take heed that you take no great matter in hand, or begin any long journey in the hours of the aforeſaid <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</hi> But of this more hereafter in this diſcourſe. Yet nevertheleſs it is manifeſt, from what hath been declared, that the Art of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is a <hi>Diabolical Divination.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 84.11. &amp; 34.9.</note> For ſaith the <hi>Prophet David, the Lord will give grace and glory, no good thing will he uphold from them that walk uprightly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From hence I gather that much, <hi>viz.</hi> That the knowledge of all good things is, and hath been by the <hi>Lord</hi> manifeſted unto his People, ſo that if the fore-knowledge of things by <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> be a good thing, it hath been by the <hi>Lord</hi> reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto his People; but the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth in no place ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie thoſe that ſeek after the fore-knowledge of things by the <hi>Starres:</hi> therefore I ſay, that the ſeeking to know fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture events by the <hi>Stars,</hi> which is <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> is not a good thing; becauſe that whatſoever is a good thing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.10.11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.2.</note> the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth not condemn it, in deriding at the profeſſors thereof.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth condemn <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> in deriding at the Profeſſors thereof: therefore <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is not a good thing. Again, whatſoever is an evil thing, the word of <hi>God</hi> doth condemn it with thoſe that practice it; but the word of <hi>God</hi> doth condemn the <hi>Practitioners</hi> of <hi>Aſtrologie:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it doth condemn <hi>Aſtrologie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now then, for as much as <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do take upon them for to divine by their Art of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar events of things belonging to Man: therefore I ſay, that the aforeſaid Art of <hi>Judicial Aſtrologie,</hi> is a <hi>Diabolical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination,</hi> becauſe it is condemned by the <hi>Scripture,</hi> with the Profeſſors thereof for a wicked Art; for ſaith the <hi>Prophet</hi> to the <hi>Law,</hi> and to the <hi>Teſtimony,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8.20.</note> if they ſpeak not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</p>
               <p>From the very word of <hi>God,</hi> you may here then very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117760:11"/>
behold, that <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> are workers in darkneſs, and their Art of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is a work of darkneſs:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider the words of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> who ſaith thus: <hi>Have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſs, but even reprove them rather.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> In which is ſet forth, that one of the firſt and chiefeſt points in <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> and without the ſaid point, <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> can do nothing, is the regarding of times, the which regarding of times, is ſuperſtition and Idolatry.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Regarding or obſerving of times, the great point in <hi>Aſtrologie.</hi>
                  </note>NOw in this place I will manifeſtly declare that which is one of the firſt and chiefeſt points in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie,</hi> and the point is this, <hi>viz. The regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or obſerving of times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I ſay, that without this point of <hi>regarding of times,</hi> the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> can do nothing in their Art of <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> for take from the Art of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> but this one thing, <hi>viz. The regarding or obſerving of times;</hi> and then it will be ſo poor an Art, that the <hi>Practitioners</hi> thereof, will be aſhamed to own it; for then it will do them no more ſervice, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> get any more pence by their Art, for telling of <hi>Fortunes,</hi> or reſolving of horary Queſtions, nor for their making of <hi>Elections;</hi> for take away <hi>Regarding of times,</hi> and then no <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> can calculate your <hi>Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> for according to the Rules of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> the very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117760:11"/>
time muſt be known, in which the Man or Woman is born, before judgement be given by the <hi>Aſtrologer:</hi> ſo in like manner, it is in queſtions, elections,<note place="margin">Mr. John Booker.</note> and all other parts of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> that this is according to the rules of <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi> it is very manifeſt from their own words; for that <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> Mr. <hi>Booker,</hi> ſaith plainly thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Aske what you will, would you reſolved be,</l>
                  <l>Obſerve your time, learn your Nativitie.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But to come more cloſe unto the matter, I find that the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do regard and obſerve times, to be either good or evil, to do ſuch, or ſuch a thing in, becauſe of the Stars and their poſitions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for they have planetary days and hours, according unto which Planets, that then rule and govern:<note place="margin">Lupton. page <hi>107.</hi> ex Haly. Abenragel.</note> The <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do account the time to be either good or evil; for ſaith one, the hour of <hi>Mars</hi> is to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred in all things, both in the beginning, and when the thing is done.</p>
               <p>And a little after he ſaith thus, <hi>viz.</hi> And as I have ſaid of <hi>Mars,</hi> ſo I ſay of <hi>Saturn,</hi> for there is never a good of them both, meaning their hours.</p>
               <p>Now this regarding of times, is <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> for theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31.</note> becauſe <hi>God</hi> hath not made any thing to be both good and evil; for ſaith <hi>Moſes, God</hi> ſaw every thing that he had made; and behold, it was very good. So that here you may ſee, after <hi>God</hi> had created all things, behold, he ſeeth all things to be very good: then from hence I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus much, that is, that the making the Starres, and ſo times according to the Stars, and their poſitions to be evil, for ſuch or ſuch a purpoſe; I ſay that this making of times evil or unfortunate according to Stars, and their ſeveral poſitions, is not of, from, nor by the appointment of <hi>God,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reaſon is, becauſe the word of <hi>God</hi> ſaith the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; for ſaith the <hi>Scripture, God</hi> ſaw all that he had made, and behold it was very good. So then from this you may ſee according to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> the hours of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> to be as good for to do any thing in them, as in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117760:12"/>
hours of <hi>Jupiter</hi> or <hi>Venus.</hi> Alſo the <hi>Moon</hi> may be in any of her Manſions, and yet you may not fear to do any lawful thing, although the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> ſhall tell you, that you have taken an infortunate election, to do your operation, by reaſon of the poſition of the Heavens. As alſo becauſe of the <hi>Moon,</hi> who is in one of her Manſions: which poſition of the <hi>Moon</hi> in the ſaid Manſion, doth ſignifie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the thing you have begun, or that it ſhall be marred by this or that means, before you can perform the work, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay, that none that fear the true <hi>God,</hi> ought to regard theſe or any ſuch like heatheniſh ſuperſtitions of the Aſtrologers, becauſe that theſe things aforeſaid are not of <hi>Gods</hi> own inſtitution; but are of mans inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that theſe things are not of Gods inſtitution: it doth evidently appear from and by the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture;</hi> for whatſoever is of <hi>Gods</hi> inſtitution, the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth bear witneſs of the ſame: but the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth bear witneſs that <hi>God</hi> made all things good,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things are good, by and from <hi>Gods</hi> inſtitution.</p>
               <p>Again, whatſoever is by, and in the <hi>Scripture</hi> condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the ſame is not of <hi>Gods</hi> inſtitution; but the regarding and obſerving of times,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.26. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.6. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10.11.</note> is by and in the <hi>Scripture</hi> condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: therefore the regarding and obſerving of times, is not of <hi>Gods</hi> inſtitution.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Arguments</hi> above written, do wholly depend upon the <hi>Scripture,</hi> as you may ſee; for the firſt Argument whoſe ſcope is to prove, that all things are good, by and from <hi>Gods</hi> inſtitution, is evidently ſeen to agree with the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> and is therefore confirmed by the <hi>Scripture,</hi> as you may ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. in theſe words, <hi>And God ſaw every thing that he had made, and behold it was very good.</hi> Now the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith plainly, that God made every thing good; ſo then we may now manifeſtly know, that God made all the Stars of Heaven good alſo according to his word, he made all years, moneths, weeks, days, and hours to be good, then that fantaſtical opinion of making a difference of days and hours, to begin a work in or upon, is in very truth, an Idolatrous and ſuperſtitious Dotage and fiction of the brains of the Aſtrologers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:117760:12"/>Alſo the other Argument, in which is declared, <hi>viz. That the regarding and obſerving of times, is not of Gods inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,</hi> is proved thus, becauſe it is condemned by and in the <hi>Scripture;</hi> for you find that <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> that great Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later, is in the <hi>Scripture</hi> reproved for his obſerving of times, among other his Idolatrous practiſes; for ſaith the <hi>Scripture</hi> thus of him, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.6. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10.</note> 
                  <hi>And he made his Sonne paſs through the fire, and obſerved times, and uſed Inchantments, and dealt with familiar ſpirits, and Wizards, &amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.6. Again in <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10. it is ſaid, <hi>viz. Let none be found among you, that uſeth Divination, or is an obſerver of times, or an Inchanter, or a Witch, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo in <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.26. it is ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall not uſe Inchantment, nor obſerve times.</hi> From theſe places of <hi>Scripture,</hi> it is plainly to be ſeen, <hi>That the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding or obſerving of times is forbidden to be uſed, and the uſe of it is condemnen for Idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now then from hence it is apparent, that <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> are very Idolaters, becauſe that they regard times, the which regarding of times is in the <hi>Scripture</hi> condemned: In the very like manner it is very apparent to all rational men, that <hi>Judicial Aſtrologie</hi> is a ſecret Diabolical Divination. I ſay ſecret, becauſe it is ſo cloſe, and a ſubtil deluſion of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> whereby <hi>Satan</hi> doth delude almoſt all men at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and maketh men which believe in this vain deluſion, <hi>viz. Aſtrologie,</hi> to think that the Stars of Heaven are the cauſes of thoſe ſtrange alterations here upon earth, in the Bodies of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Woemen,</hi> according as the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> ſay the 12. Houſes of the Heaven do ſignifie. Now what thoſe ſignifications are, is elſewhere by me ſet forth in a Figure,<note place="margin">See Chap. <hi>2.</hi> of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</note> and there you may find many of thoſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to man, which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do appropriate unto the 12. Houſes; and withall the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do ſay, that theſe 12. Houſes do give ſignification of the particular e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents of the ſaid things, and alſo of many others which are not there by me mentioned. But once again I give all men to know, how that I do here again deny, that any Man can know the iſſue, event, or end of any of the things a fore by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117760:13"/>
me, ſet down in the ſecond Chapter of this Diſcourſe, in the Figure of the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> 12. Houſes. I ſay that no man can by any lawful learning, attain to ſo much knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as thereby to know the events of the aforeſaid things; but that ſome-what may be known of the particular events of thoſe things, by unlawful and filthy Arts, I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>v. c.</hi> 31. <hi>v.</hi> 6.</note> for we find, that the <hi>Witch</hi> at <hi>Endor</hi> did predict and foretel to King <hi>Saul,</hi> that which afterwards fell out to be as the <hi>Witch</hi> had ſaid. What cauſe now then have our <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologert</hi> to brag ſo much of their <hi>Predictions,</hi> becauſe the event is as they foretold, I ſay they have no juſt cauſe to rejoyce ſo much as they do, ſeeing a wicked <hi>Witch</hi> is able to do as much. Again, their art is ſuch, that they are not able to prove lawful according to the <hi>Scripture;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it doth appear to be nothing better, then an art of learned <hi>Witch-craft:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daemonologiae Lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> according to which poſition, is the ſaying of the late <hi>King James,</hi> whoſe judgement is this, <hi>viz.</hi> as there are two ſorts of folks that may be inticed to this a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, to wit, <hi>Learned</hi> or <hi>un-learned:</hi> ſo are there two meanes, which are the firſt ſtirrers up, and feeders of their curioſity, thereby to make them to give themſelves over to the ſame: which two means I call the <hi>Devils</hi> School, and the <hi>Devils</hi> Rudiments.</p>
               <p>The Learned have their curioſity wakened up, and fed by that which I call his School.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Judicial A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie is the Devils School, for Learned men to learn orcery in.</note>This is the art of <hi>Judicial Aſtrologie;</hi> for divers men ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving attained to a great perfection in learning, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main without the ſpirit of Regeneration, and the fruits thereof, finding all natural things common, as well to the <hi>Countrey Clown</hi> as unto them; hereupon they aſſay to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe unto themſelves a greater name, by not only know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the courſe of the Heavens, Stars, and Planets; but likewiſe to climb to the knowledge of things to come thereby, which at the firſt face appearing lawful unto them, in reſpect the ground thereof ſeemeth to proceed of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral cauſes only: they are ſo allured thereby, that finding their practiſe to prove true in ſundry things, they ſtudy to the cauſe thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:117760:13"/>And ſo mounting from degree, to degree, upon the ſlipperie and uncertain ſcale of curioſitie; they are at laſt intiſed, that where lawfull Arts and Sciences fails, to ſatisfie their reſtleſs minds, even to ſtick to that black and unlawfull Science of Magick. Where finding at the firſt, that ſuch divers forms of Circles, and Conjurations, rightly joyned thereunto, will raiſe ſuch divers forms of ſpirits, to reſolve them their doubts: and attributing the doing, to the power inſeparably tyed, or inherent in the Circles, and many words of GOD, confuſedly wrapped, they blindly glory in themſelves, as if they had by their quickneſs of ingeny, made a Conqueſt of <hi>Plutoes</hi> Dominion, and were become Emperors of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Hell: where, in the mean time, (miſerable wretches) they are become in very deed, bond-ſlaves to their mortall enemy, <hi>viz:</hi> the devil, and their knowledge for all that, they preſume thereof, is nothing increaſed, except in knowing evil, and the horrors of hell for the puniſhment thereof, as <hi>Adam</hi> was, for eating of the forbidden Tree. I will here end with that ſaying of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who ſaith,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de doc. Chriſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> that the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to theſe Wiſemen is, <hi>Genus quoddam fornicationis,</hi> A ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall kinde of fornication. For all ſuch as run after this Art, or ſeek to thoſe which practiſe the ſame, I ſay they go from God; and run after the Devil a whoring.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The Poſitions and Arguments, which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> uſe, and bring for to warrant the legality of their Art of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> examined, condemned, and overthrown; Alſo their Objections opened, controverted, and Anſwered according to Reaſon.</head>
               <p>HEre I am to Diſpute, of the Poſitions and Arguments which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> make uſe of, to warrant their Art of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> by: but if the ſaid Poſitions and Arguments are warily conſidered, it will appear, that they have nothing in them, to prove the lawfulneſſe of <hi>Aſtrologicall Predictions.</hi> Of which Poſitions this is the greateſt and ſtrongeſt, and the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117760:14"/>
ſaid Poſition is this,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Chriſto: Heydon.</note> 
                  <hi>viz: That the Stars are naturall cauſes of ſuch effects, as Aſtrologers foretell.</hi> From this Poſition the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> frame many Arguments, to prove <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> a lawfull Art: for upon this very one Poſition, doth reſt and depend that great Diſcourſe of Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon,</hi> which he made in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Aſtrologie.</hi> So that if I can but remove this Prop, you ſhall ſee Sir <hi>Chriſtopher's</hi> Defence of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> drop down to the ground, and ſo with it, all our <hi>Engliſh Aſtrologers,</hi> and their Art of <hi>Judiciall Aſtrologie:</hi> for our <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> if a man queſtioneth the lawfulneſſe of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> with them, they are then at ſtand what to ſay; and have not any other way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve him that maketh a doubt of the ſaid <hi>Arts</hi> legality: But to ſend him to Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydons</hi> Defence of <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> and thus theſe idle Drones, which are not able to prove the legalitie of that <hi>Art</hi> which they daily practiſe: are glad with all their hearts to run, and hide themſelves under Sir <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher's</hi> protection, as in a Mouſe-hole; for fear they ſhould be catched in their own Arguments for it. Come out of your ſelves, you idle Drones, and prove your <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> a good, true, and lawfull Art, if you can. For if you are not able to prove the legalitie of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> by ſound and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Arguments, then for ſhame give off your practiſing of ſuch an <hi>Art,</hi> which you cannot prove lawfull and honeſt: and think not with your ſelves, that ſeeing we are not able to prove <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> a lawfull and honeſt Art yet we have on our ſide Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Gell;</hi> and they ſhall prove it for us. I give you to underſtand, I will not be ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied; for I ſay unto you <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> that if Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon,</hi> and Dr: <hi>Gell,</hi> and all the Friends <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> hath, I ſay, if I were before their faces all at once, yet then, even then I would denie, <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> to be a lawfull <hi>Art.</hi> But now to return again, to the aforeſaid Poſition of the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> which is this, <hi>viz:</hi> That the Stars are naturall cauſes of ſuch effects, as <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> foretell. Firſt I will examine this Poſition, and then ſhall we ſee, whether thoſe events which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> foretell, are cauſed by the Stars, or not. Wherfore in the firſt place we are to know, what thoſe Effects are which the <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers</hi> ſay are cauſed by the Stars. Now the effects, which the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117760:14"/>
                  <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do affirm are cauſed by the Stars, are theſe, <hi>viz:</hi> The particular events of thoſe things, belonging to man, which things are by the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> appropriate to the twelve houſes of Heaven. As for the things whoſe effects,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> his Intro: pa. 50.</note> the <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers</hi> ſay are cauſed by the Stars, I have mentioned many of them in the ſecond Chapter of this Diſcourſe, and therefore I refer you thither; for there you have them inſerted into a Figure, according as they are by the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> appropriate to the twelve Houſes. Now in this place I am to treat, of the Effects of the aforeſaid things; that is to ſay, whether,<note place="margin">A queſtion. The Anſwer.</note> or not, the effects of thoſe things are cauſed by the Stars. To this I anſwer Negatively, and ſay, that the Stars are not the cauſes, of the Effects of thoſe things belonging to man; as for example, I will inſtance in theſe particulars following, <hi>viz: Gauricus</hi> warned <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond King of France,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heydons</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</hi> p. 194. Page 81.</note> not to run at Tilt in the one and fourtieth yeer of his age, for that the Stars did then threaten a wound in his Head. <hi>Paulus tertius,</hi> warned his Son long before, of the very day of his death. Mr. <hi>Christian</hi> an Aſtrologer of Prague,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rants zovi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> fol. 97.</note> admoniſhed <hi>Ladiſlaus Jagello</hi> King of Poland (by a Prieſt,) that he ſhould beware of eminent Death, becauſe that many Planets were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned this yeer, and there happeneth an Eclipſe likewiſe of the Moon under the earth; notwithſtanding the premoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he dyed that yeer, 1434. <hi>Anno aetatis</hi> 49. Alſo <hi>Picus,</hi> being fore-told by three <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> that he ſhould not live above thirty three yeers, confirmed the prediction. Now that theſe aforeſaid events, were fore-told by the ſaid men, <hi>(viz: Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers)</hi> I confeſs; But that thoſe men could fore ſee thoſe events by the Stars, or that the Stars were Naturall cauſes of thoſe events, both theſe things I do deny, for theſe Reaſons. Firſt then I ſay, that the Stars were not naturall cauſes of thoſe afore-ſaid Events; Becauſe there is a dependence and coherence between the cauſe and the Effect, in Naturall things; but in theſe things there is none. For every Effect and Accident, doth ſhew it's Cauſe. So that Naturall and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary effects and accidents, ſhew forth Naturall and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Cauſes. Alſo Metaphyſicall or ſupernaturall Effects and Accidents, ſhew forth Metaphyſicall or ſupernaturall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117760:15"/>
cauſes. Herein the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> are beſide the matter, and are deceived in their principles; for they take Metaphyſicall or ſupernaturall effects and accidents, to be effected by Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and Elementary cauſes. Now why the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> are here deceived is this; <hi>viz:</hi> becauſe they do behold and ſee, many Alterations, changes, events and accidents, effected in mans body; Hereupon they do beleeve that the ſaid Alterations, changes, events and accidents, are effected by and from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and Elementary cauſes: becauſe the body of man, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom the ſaid things are effected, is a naturall and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary ſubſtance. Wherefore I ſay, that there are many things, which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> affirm to be effected by and from Naturall cauſes; the which Poſition I do deny, and ſay, that thoſe things are not effected by nor from Naturall and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary cauſes: But I ſay that thoſe things are Metaphyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and ſupernaturall Effects, and Accidents; and are effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and accompliſhed, in Naturall and Elementary bodies, by a Metaphyſicall and ſupernaturall Cauſe: as I will hereafter in theſe following examples declare. For whereas the <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers</hi> do impute the Flood,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Albumazar, ca. <hi>3.</hi> de Max. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junc.</p>
                     <p>Marcilius Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus <hi>in his Treatiſe of the Star that led the Wiſemen.</hi> Spine us in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtro. Mundi.</p>
                  </note> which was in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> to a certain great Conjunction of the Planets: ſo in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they ſay of the Birth of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Alſo the coming of Chriſt, and the preaching of the Goſpel, the promulgation and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the Law, the ſedition of the people, their troubles, perſecutions, baniſhments, bloodſhed, deaths, wars, theſe, and many other ſuch like things as theſe are, the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> ſay are fore-ſhewed by the Stars. Now all theſe things are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall effects, that is to ſay, they are ſuch things whoſe cauſe is not Naturall, but above Nature. So then, for as much as the cauſe of theſe things, is a Metaphyſicall Agent, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I denie, that the Effects of the aforeſaid things can be cauſed by a Phyſicall conſtellation.</p>
               <p>But now I am come to the ſecond thing which is this, <hi>viz:</hi> That no man can by the Stars foreſee ſuch Effects as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. Now that no man can by the Stars foreſee ſuch events, it is very manifeſt, for if all the Star-gazers in the world, if they were agazing all together at once on the Stars, they are not able to foreſee thoſe events in the Stars, which events
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117760:15"/>
they do not cauſe. That the Stars are not the cauſes of thoſe events, it is the ſaying of ſome of your own Authors; For, ſaith <hi>Spineus,</hi> that as well the great Conjunctions,<note place="margin">Spineus.</note> as Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtars, Comets, Eclipſes, and the like, ought not to be called the cauſes of future events, here then you may ſee, that there is ſo great contradiction, between the ſayings of the <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> and their practiſes; that all Rationall men may behold, the Art of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> to be a fooliſh lying Art: and that the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do profeſs ſuch an Art, whoſe Rules they are ignorant of. For ſometimes you ſhall have them ſay with <hi>Spineus,</hi> that the Stars are not the cauſes of Future events, but do they alwayes ſay thus? No, for if we look upon their Aſtrologicall Predictions, then ſhall we hear them ſay the very contrary. For whereas they ſaid at one time, that the great Conjunctions of the Planets, &amp;c. are not the cauſes of future events. At another time you ſhall have them ſay, that the very ſame Conjunctions do produce great Effects. As for example, I will inſtance in the ſaid <hi>Spineus</hi> who is cited afore,<note place="margin">Spineus in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtrophe Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di.</note> whoſe words are thus in one place of his book, <hi>viz.</hi> That as well the great Conjunctions, as Mock-ſtars, Comets, Eclipſes, and the like, ought not to be called the cauſes of Future Events. But this very man, <hi>Spineus</hi> writing of a Future Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe to come upon the world, in the ſame book ſaith thus, ſpeaking of the ſaid Cataſtrophe, ſubverſion, or end of the world, <hi>viz:</hi> that the principall cauſes are the great, mean, and leſſer Conjunctions of the ſuperiour Planets, the other principall cauſes are Mock-ſtars; changing of the Abſis of the Planets, Eclipſes, and the like: ſo likewiſe the Genitures of Kings, <hi>Geniturae validae regna mutant:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Segment.</hi> 7. <hi>Aph.</hi> 166.</note> Strong Genitures do change Kingdoms. Cauſes Adjutant, are Revolutions, the progreſſions of the greater Orb, of great Conjunctions; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Noah's</hi> Flood, the Birth of Chriſt, <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and the like; which things being rightly conſidered, may not only enable us to foretell the end of the world, but perhaps the time alſo: and a little after the ſame Author ſaith again, <hi>viz:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spineus in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtrophe.</note> That ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therfore the great Conjunctions of the weightier Planets, are wont to produce great effects, as the changes of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies and Kingdoms, the coming of Prophets, &amp;c. by them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117760:16"/>
alſo ſhall the dead be changed, and all things ſhall be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and again he ſaith, <hi>viz:</hi> for like as the Cauſes are, ſo ſhall the effects be; for good Conjunctions are wont to beſtow goodneſs, and good Magiſtrates; but evill Conjunctions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the contrary. Thus <hi>Spineus</hi> who is ſo much applauded by many <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> doth one while ſay one thing, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while he ſaith the very contrary to what he ſaid afore, as it is to be ſeen from his own books: for one while he ſaith that the principall cauſes of that Cataſtrophe, are the great, mean, and leſſer Conjunctions of the ſuperiour Planets, &amp;c. and not long after he ſaith, <hi>viz:</hi> that as well the great conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Planets, as Mock-ſtars, Comets, Eclipſes, &amp;c. ought not to be called the cauſes of future events, what ſhall I ſay, of ſuch an Art as is <hi>Aſtrologie?</hi> and of ſuch Artiſts, as are <hi>Aſtrologers?</hi> As for the Art of <hi>Astrologie,</hi> it is as I have elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſaid, <hi>viz:</hi> a fooliſh and lying Art. But as for the Artiſts of this Art of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> they are <hi>Aſtrologers:</hi> of them I ſay thus much, that for as much as ſome of them would needs be taken for to be Prophets: I deny that theſe <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> are any of Gods Prophets; But that they are the Devils Prophets I grant: for if in their Aſtrologicall predictions, of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular events of things belonging to Man; they at any time do predict or foretell ſuch an event, which at the time limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> doth come to paſs accordingly: yet I ſay, that the ſaid particular event could not before ſeen by the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> in it's cauſe, without the help of a Spirit. That this Poſition is according to your Art,<note place="margin">Centiloqui Ptol. Aph. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> I prove by your own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, for your great Maſter in <hi>Aſtrologie, Ptolomie</hi> ſaith, <hi>Soli autem numine afflati praedicunt particularia:</hi> that is, none but thoſe inſpired with a Daemon foretell particulars:<note place="margin">Marcilius Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus in li. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> here alſo I will bring another great Artiſt, who ſpeaking of Aſtrologicall Predictions, ſaith thus of them, <hi>viz:</hi> That ſuch predictions ſtand not by Learning, but by ſome inſtinct. Wherefore it is apparent from what theſe two great <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> have ſaid, that he who doth foretell, the particular events of things in Aſtrologicall predictions, doth not foretell thoſe events, from the Poſitians and Qualities of the Stars: But by being inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a Daemon, or by having familiarity with ſome Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:117760:16"/>Again here I bring another great Aſtrologicall Author, <hi>Cor: Agrippa,</hi> who ſaith,<note place="margin">Agrippade oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culta Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia, lib. <hi>3.</hi> Aſtrologomania.</note> that Magick and <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> cannot be ſeparated: for, ſaith <hi>Agrippa,</hi> there is ſuch affinity and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, between theſe two Arts, <hi>viz: Aſtrologie</hi> and Magick; That as Magick cannot be performed without <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> ſo <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> cannot have it's end and perfection without Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick. So then the differences is not much, whether we call theſe predictions Magicall, or Aſtrologicall predictions. Now here it is objected, <hi>viz:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Objection. Solution.</note> that the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> may ſtay himſelf in his Figure, and proceed no further. To this I anſwer: That for as much as the Knowledge of a particular event, cannot be known without the help of a Spirit; therefore I ſay, that the difference is not great, in whatſoever degree he proceedeth, ſo he proceedeth at all with the devill in his illuſions. So that if he come to the knowledge of a particular event, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by conference, or by ſome other means, then he doth proceed with the devil in his illuſions, for we are herein certified, that this thing cannot be done by any lawfull Art and Learning, but by the help of a Spirit; take that help which way you will, it is diabolicall. For that judiciall <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> either hath been, or may be altogether ſeparated from Magick; this the <hi>Aſtrolegers</hi> can never prove: if they can, then let us ſee them do it.</p>
               <p>But it is again objected by the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> as followeth, <hi>viz:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The great Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of Aſtrologers.</note> That thoſe events which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do Predict, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell; many of thoſe events do fall out to be, as the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> fore-told: therefore the Art of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is uſefull and profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the life of man. To this I anſwer thus: That to come to the knowledge of any thing by unlawfull means,<note place="margin">Anſwer. Vide Epiſt. de T. Vicars. <hi>Deut. 13.1.</hi>
                  </note> does not make the practiſe warrantable. For ſuppoſe that their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions fall out to be as they foretold, yet this makes the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> never a whit the more to be believed, nor his Art to be ever a jot the more lawfull: as it is plain in the 13. Chap. of <hi>Deut.</hi> verſe 1. <hi>If there ariſe amongſt you a Prophet, or a dreamer of dreams, and giveth thee a ſigne or a wonder. And the ſigne or wonder come to paſſe, yet ſhalt thou not hearken unto him, for the Lord your God proveth you,</hi> &amp;c. Again the devill in <hi>Samuels</hi> ſhape,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 28.11.</note> being conjured up by the Witch, did foretell unto <hi>Saul</hi> thoſe things
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117760:17"/>
which were true, and as the devill had predicted, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction proved true by the event, which fell out to be as the devill had ſaid: as you may ſee, for ſaid the divell, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.19. unto <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28.19. Chap. 31.6.</note> 
                  <hi>And to morrow ſhalt thou and thy ſons be with me, and the Lord ſhall give the host of Iſrael into the hands of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 31.6.</note> Which thing was according to the devils prediction, for in the 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.6. you ſhall finde theſe words, <hi>viz: So Saul died, and his three ſons, and his armour-bearer, and all his men that ſame day together.</hi> Moreover we find in the Acts of the Apoſtles, that the <hi>Pythoniſs</hi> there did give a true teſtimony of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of Jeſus Chriſt: thus we may ſee that the devill telleth truth ſometimes, and yet he is ſtill the father of lyes. Now here you may plainly ſee, that the devils can foretell what ſhall be the events of ſome things; ſo then it being ſo, that God is ſometimes pleaſed, to permit unto the devils, the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge of ſome things, and that the ſaid devils do many times declare the future events of things as is aforeſaid. Therefore I ſay, for this cauſe we are not to think it a ſtrange thing, in that we ſometimes ſee the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> foretell, that which afterwards doth come to paſs, and when the thing is come to paſs, we are not then to give ever the more credit to the <hi>Aſtrologer;</hi> nor yet to think <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> to be any whit the law fuller; becauſe the event falleth out to be, as the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> had afore predicted. For, if becauſe the event falleth out to be true, or ſhall come to paſſe according to the prediction, I ſay if any ſhall beleeve <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> to be a lawfull Art, from this ground (<hi>viz:</hi> Becauſe thoſe things foretold by the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> many times fall out to be true, and ſo come to paſs as they predicted) again I ſay if they have no better arguments to prove the legallity of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> then this of the event anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the prediction. Here then I ſay to all rationall men, <hi>viz:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> that Magick, Conjuration, Witch-craft, and all ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable, wicked and unclean Arts may by the aforeſaid argument, be proved to be as lawfull as is the Art of <hi>Judiciall Aſtrologie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28.19. 1 Sam. 31.6.</note> As for example, I will inſtance in the death of King <hi>Saul</hi> with his ſonnes, and the deſtruction of his great Armie, for we finde that the witch at <hi>Endor</hi> having conjured up the divell for to reſolve the King of his doubts, the ſaid divell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117760:17"/>
raiſed up by the <hi>Witches</hi> art, anſwereth unto the <hi>King</hi> after this manner, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.19</note> 
                  <hi>To morrow ſhalt thou and thy Sonnes be with me, the Lord ſhall deliver alſo the Hoſt of Iſrael into the hand of the Philiſtims, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that this <hi>Prediction</hi> fell out to be true,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.6.</note> according to the <hi>Devils</hi> predicting of the ſame, none can deny; for ſaith the <hi>Scripture, ſo Saul dyed, and his three Sonnes, and his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour-bearer, and all his men that ſame day together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then from hence you may ſee the aforeſaid argument, cannot prove the legality of the art of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> any more, then it can prove the lawfulneſs of the <hi>Witch</hi> and her art, in raiſing up the <hi>Devil</hi> at <hi>Endor:</hi> wherefore we may evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently underſtand from hence as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> What the greateſt and ſtrongeſt arguments are, which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> can, or are able to bring to prove the legality of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> from and by: I ſay that <hi>Magick Conjuration</hi> and <hi>Witch-craft,</hi> may from and by the ſaid argument, be proved and warranted, as lawful and as honeſt as <hi>Judicial Aſtrologie;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.18. <hi>Mic.</hi> 5.12.</note> but how lawful and honeſt <hi>Witch-craft</hi> is, I leave unto all men for to judge from theſe places of <hi>Scripture;</hi> for it is ſaid in <hi>Exod</hi> 22.18. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer a Witch to live,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain it is ſaid by the <hi>Lord God</hi> in <hi>Mica,</hi> 5.12. <hi>and I will cut off Witch-crafts out of thine hand, and thou ſhalt have no more Sooth-ſayers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return again to my purpoſe, I have declared a little afore, that the greateſt and ſtrongeſt arguments that are ſet forth by the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> for to prove the legality of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> by, is this, <hi>viz.</hi> The event falling out to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Prediction.</hi> Now that this is the beſt,<note place="margin">The greateſt argument the Aſtrologers have to prove the legality of their art.</note> and ſtrongeſt of all the arguments, which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> can bring and produce, to warrant the legality of their ſaid art of <hi>Judicial Aſtrologie</hi> by.</p>
               <p>I ſay it is evidently to be ſeen, that this is their greateſt and ſtrongeſt argument, as it doth plainly appear by their own words and confeſſions, written by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their own Books, as you ſhall ſee I will here again manifeſtly prove, although the ſame is elſe-where by me done.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:117760:18"/>
                  <note place="margin">Sir Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Heydon in his defence of Aſtrologie, fol, <hi>195.</hi>
                  </note>But to begin, I think it is my beſt way, to ſet their Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion in the firſt place, becauſe if any man queſtioneth with our <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> about the lawfulneſs of their Art, they in all the haſte and ſpeed as may poſſible be done, ſend him unto their Champion Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon</hi>'s Defence of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> where he may have a full reſolution of all his queſtions and doubts which he hath ag inſt <hi>Aſtrologie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now ſeeing we are in a Diſpute about the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do commonly bring, to prove their art of Aſtrology a lawful art: now then ſeeing Sir <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> is the chiefeſt of our Aſtrologers, and unto him they ſend all that gainſay their art; therefore let us hear what he can ſay for Aſtrology.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heydon.</hi> 195.</note>Now what he ſaith, made him believe Aſtrology to be a lawful art, is onely, becauſe he had ſeen the event fall out true according to the Prediction; as it doth plainly appear by his own words, which are as followeth in the 195 page of his Diſcourſe, where he ſaith thus, viz.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I, for my part (ſaith he) do freely confeſs, that there is no one thing that hath made me ſo confident in the validity of this art, as that which I have ſeen to fall out true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the great Artiſt of Aſtrology, in few words, hath told us, what his ſtrongeſt argument is, whereby he can prove Aſtrology a lawful and a mighty powerful art: now if this be a ſufficient warrant, to make a man confident in the validity of an art,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.</note> becauſe he ſeeth the Predictions fall out true; then may theſe Aſtrologers be as confident, in the validity of Witchcraft, as they can be of the legality of Aſtrology by their own argument; for becauſe the greateſt and ſtrongeſt argument, which all of them uſe to plead the validity of Aſtrology by, is this, Becauſe they ſee their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions fall out true.</p>
               <p>Again, to this I anſwer, as I ſaid before, That this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth prove Aſtrology no more to be a lawful art, then it doth prove Witchcraft to be lawful; for all that which was foretold unto <hi>Saul</hi> by Witchcraft fell out true:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117760:18"/>
Therefore Witchcraft is as lawful as Aſtrology, by the beſt argument of the Aſtrologers.</p>
               <p>Now that this is the beſt and ſtrongeſt argument, which the Aſtrologers have to warrant the legality of Aſtrology by, this, I ſay, I will prove by their own words and confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as I ſaid afore; and I will fetch out him firſt into the light, unto whom they all run to hide themſelves in the dark.</p>
               <p>He it is, whom I cited a little afore,<note place="margin">Heydon. fol. <hi>195.</hi>
                  </note> Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon</hi> in his Defence of Aſtrology, ſaith thus, viz. <hi>I, for my part (ſaith he) do freely confeſſe, that there is no one thing that hath made me ſo confident in the validity of this Art, as that which I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fall out true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now you having here underſtood what Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon's</hi> great argument for Aſtrology is,<note place="margin">Mr. Lilly. page <hi>148.</hi> of his Intr.</note> in the next place you ſhall hear what Mr. <hi>William Lillie</hi> hath declared to be his great argument, for the verity or truth of Aſtrology; his words are thus, ſpeaking of the markes, moles, or ſcars of the querent, (ſaith he) <hi>I have many times admired at the verity hereof, and it hath been one main argument of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging ſo far in all the parts of Aſtrologie, for very rarely you ſhall find theſe rules fail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus Mr. <hi>Lillie,</hi> with his feeble argument for the verity of Aſtrologie, which argument of his, can prove Aſtrology to be no better then Witchcraft.</p>
               <p>But I have another of our Engliſh Star-maſters,<note place="margin">Mr. Booker in his Bloody Almanack.</note> Mr. <hi>Booker,</hi> who writing of the conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> ſaith thus, viz.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am herein</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>much incouraged by thoſe labours of my friend</hi> Mr. <hi>Lillie, not onely printed in theſe times, but made more memorable in the ſucceſs, I have obſerved, hath followed his Astrological Predictions; a few of which I will repeat, that the miſguided infancy against Astrologie, may not be deſtitute of ſufficient testimony in his onely Writings of the verity of that Art; by which art, at this time, I write the enſuing Diſcourſe.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Booker.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, my Reader, conſider what theſe aforeſaid
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117760:19"/>
                  <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> have ſaid for the verity of their art of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> and thou ſhalt ſee that their beſt and ſtrongeſt arguments that they can produce to warrant the legality and verity of <hi>A rologie</hi> by.</p>
               <p>I ſay, thou <hi>Reader</hi> mayſt ſee, that by their own arguments the legality and verity of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is proved no more; then the legality and verity of <hi>Witch-craft,</hi> by their own afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid argument of the event falling out, according to the <hi>Prediction.</hi> But ſeeing I have ſufficiently declared againſt this argument, in ſhewing the inſufficiency of the ſame to prove <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> any better then <hi>Witch-craft:</hi> therefore I here leave it, and ſo proceed on to the next poſition of the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> wherein they do affirm, that the World is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by <hi>Stars</hi> and <hi>Angels.</hi> Now their ſaid poſition is this, <hi>viz.</hi> that from the beginning of the World there were 7. Spirits appointed as Rulers to the 7. Planets, and every one of theſe Spirits ruleth the World 354. years, and 4. months in order.<note place="margin">Tritemius. Avenazre.</note> Now then for as much as I am here to write of the <hi>Aſtrologers Planetary Angels</hi> or <hi>Spirits,</hi> therefore I will evidently ſet forth to the view of all men, what the ſaid <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Spirits</hi> are, that ſo all rational men may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and ſee, how the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> would delude others, as they themſelves are deluded, for that they believe a lye, in their affirming <hi>Gods</hi> governing of the World by planetary <hi>Angels,</hi> which ſaid planetary <hi>Angels</hi> are very <hi>Devils.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay again, and again, I will affirm it as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> 7. planetary <hi>Angels,</hi> are no other <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Spirits,</hi> then thoſe 7. chief <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Spirits,</hi> which are the only <hi>Agents</hi> for the <hi>Magicians</hi> and <hi>Conjurers</hi> in their ſeveral operations of conjuration, that this is truth, I am able to prove by the writings of ſome of your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, and others. Alſo I can bear witneſs to the ſame, from my own experience;<note place="margin">Mr. Lilly. Tritemim. Avenazre,</note> for you <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> ſay, that the names of your <hi>Planetary Angels</hi> are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Caſſiel,</hi> 2. <hi>Zachariel.</hi> 3. <hi>Samael.</hi> 4. <hi>Michael.</hi> 5. <hi>Anael.</hi> 6. <hi>Raphael,</hi> 7. <hi>Gabriel.</hi> Thus they are alſo called by the <hi>Magicians,</hi> and <hi>Conjurers,</hi> as you ſee here ſet forth by the <hi>Aſtrologers;</hi> for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117760:19"/>
the <hi>Magi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ians</hi> know them by theſe names, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Caſſiel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heptameron Petri de Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bano.</note> 2. <hi>Zachariel.</hi> 3. <hi>Samael.</hi> 4. <hi>Michael.</hi> 5. <hi>Anael.</hi> 6. <hi>Raphael.</hi> 7. <hi>Gabriel.</hi> Aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, theſe 7. <hi>Angels</hi> are thus by the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> appropriate unto the 7. <hi>Planets, viz.</hi> unto <hi>Saturn, Caſſiel,</hi> unto <hi>Jupiter, Zachariel,</hi> unto <hi>Mars, Samael,</hi> unto the <hi>Sunne, Michael,</hi> unto <hi>Venus, Anael,</hi> unto <hi>Mercury, Raphael,</hi> unto the <hi>Moon, Gabriel:</hi> and as you ſee they are appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate unto the 7. <hi>Planets</hi> by the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> even ſo in the very ſame manner, they are appropriate unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Planets,</hi> by the <hi>Magicians.</hi> Alſo in like manner as the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do divide the days of the week amongſt the 7. <hi>Planets,</hi> and ſo from hence they call the 7. days of the week after the names of the <hi>Planets,</hi> by appropriating the days of the week unto the <hi>Planets</hi> as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> unto the <hi>Planet Saturn,</hi> they give <hi>Saturday,</hi> unto <hi>Jupiter Thurſday,</hi> unto <hi>Mars Tueſday,</hi> unto the <hi>Sun Sunday,</hi> unto <hi>Venus Fryday,</hi> unto <hi>Mercury Wedneſday,</hi> unto the <hi>Moon Munday:</hi> even ſo do the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians.</hi> Moreover, the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do divide the day into 12. equal parts, whether the day be long or ſhort: theſe parts they call planetary hours, theſe planetary hours the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> appropriate unto the 7. <hi>Planets</hi> for them to rule in: from hence it is, that they are called planetary hours. After this manner do the <hi>Magicians</hi> and <hi>Conjurers</hi> alſo, and as you here ſee, how <hi>Astrologie</hi> and <hi>Magick</hi> do begin to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, even ſo do they end together; for there is ſuch a ſtrong tye between theſe 2. arts, that they cannot be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated one from the other, without a renting of them both in peeces. But now here to return again to my former mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter where I laid down this poſition, <hi>viz.</hi> That the 7. <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netary Angels</hi> of the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> are 7. <hi>Devils, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. Booker in his this years Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack. <hi>1651.</hi>
                  </note> Now whereas Mr. <hi>Booker</hi> ſaith, who dare or can deny <hi>Gods Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> of the World by <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Stars:</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Dr. <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> hath made a Sermon of <hi>Gods Government</hi> of the World by <hi>Stars</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> who in the ſame Sermon ſaith thus in the 2. page of his ſaid Sermon, <hi>viz And therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the times of reſtitution of all things, Act.</hi> 3.21. <hi>which are at hand,</hi> appear before the many oppreſſed divine truths be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117760:20"/>
ſet free:<note place="margin">Dr. Gells Sermon, p. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> the truths in nature, which together with thoſe other, have been long time decryed and trodden under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, muſt be revealed and publickly made known. Such is <hi>Gods Government</hi> of the World by <hi>Stars</hi> and <hi>Angels.</hi> Thus Dr. <hi>Gell</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Sermon,</hi> doth in divers places ſpeak of <hi>Gods Government</hi> of the World by <hi>Stars</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> and ſo he being deluded with a ſuperſtitious and heatheniſh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, of the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> and <hi>Magicians,</hi> ſtriveth and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth with all the might and power he hath to delude o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as he and his <hi>Auditory</hi> are deluded, in that they be of a heatheniſh opinion concerning the <hi>Stars,</hi> and alſo have a good conceit of the <hi>Devils,</hi> as if <hi>God</hi> did govern the World by them.<note place="margin">
                     <p>Dr. Gells Ser. page <hi>23.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr Booker in his Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack. <hi>1651.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> Now ſeeing Dr. <hi>Gell,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Booker</hi> ſay, who can deny, or who dare deny, <hi>Gods Government</hi> of the World by <hi>Stars</hi> and <hi>Angels?</hi> therefore I ſay, and hereby I give them to know, and ſo with them all other of the ſame ſociety to underſtand, that I dare and can deny their ſaid poſition, in which they do affirm the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the World by <hi>Stars</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> the which I do deny as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> That for as much as the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that the World is governed by <hi>ſecundarian Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> which ſaid <hi>ſecundarian Intelligences,</hi> are <hi>Stars, Planets, Conſtellations</hi> and <hi>Spirits.</hi> Therefore I do deny the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid aſſertion of the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> for theſe reaſons following, <hi>viz.</hi> That whatſoever is immediately governed by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of <hi>God</hi> only, the ſame is not governed by <hi>ſecundari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Intelligences;</hi> but the whole life of Man is governed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly by the providence of <hi>God</hi> only: therefore I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that Mans life is governed by the <hi>ſecundarian Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> which are <hi>Stars</hi> and <hi>Angels:</hi> Now that the life of Man is governed by the providence of God only, I prove it thus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 38.41. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.9.</note> 
                  <hi>That he who provideth for the Raven his food, the ſame it is who only governeth the whole life of Man;</hi> but ſaith the Scripture, <hi>The Lord God, he giveth to the Beaſt his Food, and to the young Ravens which cry:</hi> therefore it is the living God that governeth the whole courſe of the life of Man, and not only man; but alſo the whole courſe of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117760:20"/>
World likewiſe; for, behold the Fowles of the Air,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.26.</note> 
                  <hi>for they ſowe not, neither do they reap, nor gather into Barns; yet your heavenly Father feedeth them.</hi> Again,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.29.30.</note> 
                  <hi>are not two Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows ſold for a Farthing? and one of them ſhall not fall on the ground without your Father.</hi> But the very hairs of your head are all numbred; ſo that a <hi>Sparrow</hi> cannot fall, nor a hair of my head periſh, without the good will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of my heavenly <hi>Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore we may ſee plainly, that God, the living God, doth govern all the World by his only wiſdom and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: So that we ſee here is no place for the <hi>ſecundarian Intelligences</hi> of the <hi>Aſtrologians;</hi> whereupon it is evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſeen, that their <hi>ſecundarian Intelligences,</hi> are only pernitious and ſuperſtitious Fables, whereby the <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> are deluded by the <hi>Devil,</hi> in that they Idolize the <hi>Starres,</hi> and are deceived in their <hi>Planetary Angels,</hi> who they think are the good <hi>Angels</hi> of God; but the <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> and all other that think thoſe 7. <hi>Angels</hi> which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> call <hi>Planetary Angels,</hi> are good <hi>Angels.</hi> I ſay if any man ſay that the ſaid <hi>Angels</hi> are good, I ſay that all ſuch men are deluded; for whoſoever ſaith that evil is good, the ſame is deluded; but <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do call evil good, in that they affirm the <hi>Planetary Angels</hi> to be good <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> the which ſaid <hi>Angels,</hi> are <hi>Devils,</hi> as I ſaid afore; for becauſe that no man can by <hi>Conjurations</hi> cauſe the good <hi>Angels</hi> to appear in a viſible form at his will and pleaſure; But ſome man can cauſe the <hi>Planetary Angels</hi> to appear in a viſible form at his will and pleaſure, by <hi>Conjuration:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Planetary Angels</hi> are not good <hi>Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover I ſay, that theſe 7. <hi>Planetary Angels</hi> of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strologers,</hi> are the chief agents for <hi>Conjurors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reader,</hi> to the end that thou in this place mayſt have ſeen how that the ſaid <hi>Planetary Angels</hi> of the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> are as I have aforeſaid told thee, <hi>viz.</hi> Seven <hi>Devils</hi> which are alſo the <hi>Magicians</hi> chief agents in all <hi>Magical</hi> operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:117760:21"/>I ſay, I did purpoſe with my ſelf at the firſt, when I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun this work againſt <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> to have ſhewed how <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie</hi> is the foundation of <hi>Magick:</hi> as alſo I thought to have ſet forth how theſe <hi>Planetary Angels</hi> are the chief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents for the <hi>Magicians,</hi> in their ſeveral operations of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe, I could here have ſet forth unto thy view, their Figures, Circles, and many ſuch things not fitting to be mentioned.</p>
               <p>Alſo I could have ſhewed unto thee, how theſe 7. <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netary Angels</hi> are to be called upon by the <hi>Magician.</hi> To ſpeak briefly of the matter, I could have here ſhewen unto thee, the whole body of <hi>Magick,</hi> the which if I had done, when thou hadſt ſeen it,<note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie,</hi> in the practiſe.</note> thou wouldeſt have told me that <hi>Magick</hi> is as lawful as <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> for the difference that is between <hi>Magick</hi> and <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> is only in the practiſe; for whereas the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> doth work by his Houſes, and from the poſitions of the <hi>Stars</hi> in them, he doth from thence with his ſuperſtitious regarding of times, conjecture of the events of things: but the <hi>Magician</hi> doth work af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, for the <hi>Magician</hi> having by <hi>Conjuration,</hi> called upon the <hi>Aſtrologers Planetary Angels,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The ſaid <hi>Angels</hi> do appear in many forms, but at the length, they appearing only which ſhould, and in their proper forms, they will ſay unto the <hi>Magician, Pete quid vis.</hi> &amp;c. which the <hi>Magician</hi> having made known, then the ſaid Spirits will reſolve him of his doubts, and if the <hi>Magician</hi> hath any thing for the ſaid <hi>Angels</hi> to perform and do, then will they (if God permit) accompliſh the ſame according to the deſire of the <hi>Magician.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here I could have declared more of the myſtery of this wicked art; but why I will ſay no more of the ſame at this time, this is my reaſon, becauſe if I ſhould here unfold and lay open the Rules of this art, men of corrupt hearts who are now ignorant of that wicked art, when they ſaw the Rules of the ſame made manifeſt, although they are as unclean, and as wicked as the very <hi>Devil:</hi> yet I ſay, thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:117760:21"/>
men would take the Rules of the ſaid art, and joyn them together again, and ſo I ſhould contrary to my own deſire, help to build up that which I am appointed to deſtroy: wherefore it is ſufficient, that I have declared the illegality of the aforeſaid arts. But one word more, and then I have done, whereas I ſaid a little before, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> doth work by his Houſes, and from the poſitions of the <hi>Star</hi> in them, he doth from thence with his ſuperſtitious regarding of times, conjecture of the events of things; that is to ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> that whereas the <hi>Magician</hi> doth in his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe work, and underſtand plainly from the <hi>Planetary An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> by conferring with them, I ſay the <hi>Magician</hi> is herein fully reſolved, by this way of conference, what ſhall be the event of any thing he deſires to know, (if the <hi>Devils</hi> know it; But for as much as <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do not work in this way of conference with the <hi>Planetary Angels:</hi> therefore the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> have another way whereby they work: now in the way the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> go, they know things but only by conjecture; and the reaſon why they cannot determine poſitively in things, as can the <hi>Magicians,</hi> is this, becauſe the <hi>Magicians</hi> have the help of the Devils, by having conference with them. Now the Devil maketh out himſelf unto the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> in a dark hidden way, that the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> cannot ſee him, although he work continually by him. Now then the way by which the Devil and the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> do work together, is briefly thus, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious regarding of times, and their erecting of a figure, with their obſerving the poſition of the Stars in their ſaid figure; to this end, that ſo they might know the events of particular things: I ſay that this regarding of time, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting of a figure, with the obſerving of the Stars therein, to the end aforeſaid: I ſay it is nothing elſe but vain Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, whereby the <hi>Planetary Angels</hi> do come to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and know, what it is the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> would foretel, or what the thing is, of which the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> would predict and foretel the event thereof. So then the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure being erected, he doth from thence conjecture what
<pb facs="tcp:117760:22"/>
ſhall be the event of the thing, for which the figure was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected. Now the Aſtrologer having thus delivered his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, from thence forth the Planetary Angels do all that they are able (God permitting them) to bring to paſſe that which the Aſtrologer did foretel: Now why the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil doth all this, it is to this end, that ſo he may uphold and maintain his Kingdom of darkneſs.</p>
               <p>Thus Reader, I will here make an end, and if thou haſt any thing to ſay againſt me, becauſe I have denied Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie to be a lawful Art, thou knoweſt where I have my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding place.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117760:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
